I was recently faced with one of those
really hard, really big decisions. For
me, it had to do with my career path and
deciding whether or not to commit myself
to a very new, very different direction.
You know, if there's one thing that I
learned from the 18 years of being in
business for myself, it's that these big
hard decisions, they come up from time
to time and they really do make an
impact on the bigger picture trajectory
of your career, of your business, maybe
even your life. And so having gone
through a couple of these really big
trajectory changing decision moments in
my career, I really do feel the weight
of the importance and the weight of
taking ownership of these decisions when
they come up because we we do have to
own them. We have to own how we approach
the decision-m process and ultimately we
have to own our final decision and the
aftermath. Now, I mean, I can tell you
I'm two days out from having made my
final decision on this thing. And man, I
feel a relief. I feel that I feel some
freedom. I feel some excitement and
motivation because now I know now I know
the the decision has been made and all I
need to do is is move forward. And I
learned a lot about myself on the other
side of this decision. But a few days
prior to that, I was having a rough
time. I was deep in it. I was feeling
the stress. I was feeling the weight uh
and the uncertainty. Um and I was really
questioning a lot of assumptions that I
had about myself, about my business,
about my career, about this opportunity
that I was faced with. And then it
started to compound because I started to
become a little frustrated with how much
I was struggling with this particular
decision. So, not just dealing with the
uncertainty of which direction to take
here, but the frustration with how much
weight and how much time and energy and
focus this decision was pulling from me.
But, you know, this wasn't the first
time that I was faced with one of these
big hard decisions, right? There have
been a few times where I made the
decision to sell and exit my business.
Earlier in my career, I made the
decision to voluntarily leave a good
steady salary position to go out on my
own and start my own business, become
self-employed. And so, having gone
through this decision-making process
several times in my career, especially a
few that did make a huge impact on the
the trajectory of my career, both good
and bad. Some decisions I look back on
that I'm I'm happy with those decisions
and some I I do end up regretting and I
learn from them. But I have picked up an
insight or two or three about what it
means to own these decisions and how to
move forward with them. And so I want to
share those with you. The first is to
get clear on exactly what type of
decision you are faced with here because
that really matters. The second is about
asking advice from others and the right
way and the wrong way to do that. And
the third is to understand the struggle
that you're experiencing behind the
decision and how you can use that to
your advantage. Okay. So, when one of
these hard decisions comes up, the first
thing that I'm thinking about is what
type of decision is this really? Is it
an easily undoable decision or is it
something that's going to have a
permanent outcome that I can't undo or
walk back? The truth is, the vast
majority of seemingly really hard,
difficult decisions are undoable.
There's very very few decisions in life
or in your career or in your business
that you truly can't walk back or undo
or quit and try the other direction.
Sometimes you can even undo or change
direction pretty quickly after realizing
that it's that you've made the wrong
call. And so when you recognize that
even though this might be a big decision
with a lot of high impact, if you're
confident that at the end of the day you
could easily undo it, then your best bet
is to try to make the decision sooner
rather than later. Waiting around and
waffling and hoping for new information
to arise is not going to make that
decision any easier. In that situation,
the wrong decision is no decision.
You're much better off just moving
forward one way or the other, whichever
way your gut is pointing you to and
going with that until you realize that
maybe that was wrong and you can
iterate, pivot, undo, quit, and try
another direction. Not the end of the
world. It happens. But then every now
and again, you are faced with one of
those decisions that is actually
permanent. In my case, a few times in my
career, I made the decision to sell and
exit my own business. Can't undo that
one. Once it's sold, once somebody else
takes ownership, I can't get it back and
I have to own that decision. And it's
those decisions where I know that the
outcome truly is permanent, those are
the ones that I have a lot harder time
dealing with. And those are the ones
that I think do deserve more time and
more deliberation and taking a bit more
care before you truly commit. You know,
don't overdo it. And I still believe
that just waiting and waiting for more
information to reveal itself is not
going to be very helpful. But spending
the extra time can help you uncover
what's truly important to you. Now,
there's one caveat here, and this almost
tripped me up this past week when I was
dealing with another one of these big
decisions. Sometimes they can disguise
themselves as a permanent decision when
in reality it is an undoable decision.
the options that you have might feel
like once you choose one you can't
really walk it back or you can't do it
over when in reality sometimes it just
takes a bit of time to be able to undo
it or maybe it's a little bit more
complicated but at the end of the day
you can change course that that can
happen too so it's just something to be
aware of another thing that I've picked
up about the decision-m process is about
seeking advice from others seeking
advice from friends from adviserss maybe
from family. There's a right way and a
wrong way to do it. The wrong way is to
ask others what should I do. Tell me
which decision to make. That is just too
much to ask of anyone else because
there's no way that any other person can
possibly know what the right decision or
wrong decision is for you. Only you know
that. Only you can actually determine
that. There are so many variables and
factors at play. Even if it's someone
who has gone through similar decisions
in the past or even if it's someone who
is further ahead than you or more
experienced or someone that you look up
to, you might really trust their opinion
and you should, but still there's no way
that they know the right decision or the
wrong decision for you. Really, no
matter what it is, ultimately it's a
very personal thing. Does that mean you
shouldn't seek advice? No, of course
not. I actually find immense value from
reaching out to people that I trust and
respect and especially people who who
have navigated the path that I have like
my fellow business owner friends. But
what I'm looking for when I seek advice
and I think this is a better way to
approach the advice seeking process and
that that is to just look for their
reactions. I mostly phrase my advice in
terms of like here's what I'm thinking.
Here's where I'm leaning on this and
these are the factors that I'm weighing
for me and and what they mean to me. How
does that land with you? I'm looking for
reactions. I'm looking for impressions.
And those reactions can help to nudge me
in certain ways or at least point my
attention to certain data points that I
might have been a little bit blind to or
I might have not been looking at as
closely. You know, just this past week
when I was asking for advice from some
friends on this big decision I was
facing, they were able to shed some
light on some key data points that I was
sort of glossing over and not giving
enough importance. And it just made me
give give those items a second look. And
that started to inform where my gut was
pointing. And it did help my final
decision take shape. And you know, when
seeking advice, especially from those
closest to you, like your family and
close friends, typically what they care
about is your happiness. And that's what
I'm looking for when I seek advice from
those closest to me is they know me on a
personal level. So they know what would
make me happy and what would not make me
happy or at least they're able to
question like is that really going to
make you happy? And that's what matters
to them most. You know, they're not here
and and they're not in a position to
think strategically about, well, should
we move this chess piece or that chess
piece? What does that mean for your
career? At the end of the day, they
don't actually care about that. What
they care about is, am I happy? Right?
And ultimately, that's what I care
about, too. And so that's why I seek
advice from those closest to me.
Sometimes that's the hardest part about
making a big decision is like I don't
even really know which way is going to
make me happy or regret. So that's how I
think about the advice piece. All right.
The last insight that I have on the
decision-m process is something that I
think I just picked up on this most
recent goaround with uh facing a
decision and that is understanding the
struggle behind the decision. Why am I
struggling to make this decision?
Understanding that why, understanding
where the struggle comes from can
actually work to your advantage. So,
here's what I mean. At the start of this
video, I talked about the compounding
effect of the stress that goes into
deciding one way or another, right?
First, you have the surface level.
Should I choose path A or path B? But
then it starts to compound and you start
to think, why am I having such a hard
time deciding one way or the other?
Making these decisions should be easier.
Why am I struggling? I found that most
of the time that struggle is rooted in
the fact that you're personally leaning
toward the path that is more
unconventional. You know, because the
conventional path, the seemingly correct
path, the path that others probably look
at and think is correct, and the path
that most people probably would take is
not the one that you and your gut and
your instinct are leaning toward. And
and so that's what's causing the second
guessing and questioning of yourself,
like why am I feeling and why am I
thinking in this unconventional way? You
know, that's what happened to me in this
most recent decision where one path was
a career opportunity that I know that
thousands of people would dream of
landing this type of opportunity. And I
was actually in a small group of people
who could potentially realize that as as
a new reality. But I was struggling with
this decision because of that fact. It
it seemed so attractive by all these
different measures. But why was it not a
no-brainer for me? It's it's a
no-brainer for a lot of other people,
but why is it not one for me? And that's
what led me to the realization that my
instinct, my gut, my personal values,
what I truly want doesn't align with
that path. And that's why I ultimately
decided to go the other way, which is
unconventional. And it was actually that
struggle that led to what clicked for me
and what led me to the final decision to
decide against that approach and go this
way. And once I made the decision, I
felt that freedom. I felt a new sense of
motivation. I'm feeling that fire to
move forward in this in this reality
that I have accepted and I'm excited.
And so I'm on the other side of that.
And so that's how you can actually use
your struggle under the weight of a big
decision to find what it is that's most
important to you. Find what you value
and follow that gut instinct because at
the end of the day, that's always your
best bet. So that's how I think about
these hard decisions in my business and
in my career. And you know, having owned
and run my own business for the last 18
years, most of that bootstrapped and
self-funded, which has its own set of
challenges, I can tell you these these
decisions keep coming up. And so, I
actually recorded another video a couple
of weeks ago about what it is to
bootstrap a business and what that
actually means to me. So, I invite you
to check that one out next and let me
know what you think in the comments. Hey
for watching.